Guide to the Julia Ruuttila Papers 1878-2004
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Julia Ruuttila Papers
1878-2004
1935-1970
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss250
Ruuttila, Julia, 1907-1991
5 linear ft. (6 document cases, 2 oversize folders)
Papers of a prominent Northwest labor activist and journalist include correspondence, ephemera, legal papers, manuscripts, and published materials.
Biography of Julia Ruuttila:
Julia Ruuttila (1907-1991) was born in Eugene, Oregon, to John and Ella Godman, who were labor and women's suffrage activists. She grew up in logging camps and on a farm, as well as in Eugene. After one short-lived early marriage to William Bowen, Julia attended the University of Oregon during the 1925-1926 school year and then married Maurice "Butch" Bertram and had her only child, Michael Jack, in 1928. After living in California, Oregon, Denver and Chicago, the Bertrams returned to Oregon in early 1929. Butch worked at the West Oregon lumber mill in Linnton, and Julia bought a typewriter. In 1943, Julia divorced Butch and married Ben Eaton, a seaman. That marriage lasted until 1946. She married Oscar Ruuttila in 1951, and they lived in Astoria, Oregon, until his sudden death from a heart attack in 1962. They had no children but raised Julia's grandson, Shane McDonald.
Julia's labor activism included organizing for the woodworkers' union, and she was instrumental in organizing women's auxiliaries of the woodworkers' and longshoremen's unions. In 1936, Julia created the Free Ray Becker Committee to obtain the release of the last IWW prisoner from the Centralia, Washington, tragedy of 1919. She became a lifelong activist on behalf of workers, for peace, and against racial prejudice and political repression, forming many committees and participating in many protests.
Although she wrote poetry, novels, and stories, Julia became best known for her journalism. She wrote for union papers, The Timber Worker (International Woodworkers of America) and the Dispatcher (International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union); the People's W orld; and for Federated Press, a news service. She wrote under several names: Julia Godman, Julia Bertram, Julia Eaton, and Julia Ruuttila, as well as pen names, Kathleen Cronin and Kathleen Ruuttila.
After World War II, Julia worked as a secretary for the State Public Welfare Commission before being dismissed for her writing and political activities. She then worked as a secretary for the Longshoremen's Union and fishermen's unions. In 1956, she was subpoenaed to testify at the House Un-American Activities Committee hearings in Seattle, Washington, based in part on her participation in the Oregon Committee for Protection of the Foreign Born. She had been the subject of FBI surveillance since the early 1940s.
Julia continued her journalism and activism into old age and spent much of 1970 doing interviews and research on Louise Bryant for Virginia Gardner, who published Friend and Lover: The Life of Louise Bryant in 1982. Ill health forced Julia to move to the Marshall Union Manor, a union-operated retirement home, in 1976. Soon, she was editing the Manor's newsletter. Julia became a historical resource herself, frequently speaking to high school and college classes and organizations on labor, civil rights, and women's history. She spent the last years of her life with her grandson, Shane, and his family in Anchorage, Alaska, where she continued to participate in committees and protests.
NOTE: Sticking to the Union: An Oral History of the Life and Times of Julia Ruuttila by Sandy Polishuk provides a full account of Julia's life, much of it in her own words.
The Julia Ruuttila Papers consist of correspondence, ephemera, legal papers, interview transcripts and reports, manuscripts, published materials, and her FBI File, which was obtained by her biographer, Sandy Polishuk, under the Freedom of Information Act.
Correspondence, manuscripts, and published materials do not represent her full output but provide a good sampling of her career as a journalist and writer and of her wide-ranging activities on behalf of labor, civil rights, and peace movements protesting the Vietnam and Gulf wars. The collection also reflects her research contributions to a biography of Louise Bryant, Friend and Lover, by Virginia Gardner.
Much of the collection is original materials, but it also includes photocopied materials. A few of these were collected by Julia Ruuttila in the course of her work, but most of the photocopies, including family correspondence, were collected by Sandy Polishuk.
The collection includes Julia's own contributions to the history of labor, civil rights, and peace movements as reflected in her correspondence, manuscripts, and published materials. Although most of her published work is journalistic in nature, the collection reflects her love of writing poetry and includes an unpublished novel.
The collection is organized into the following series and subseries:
Series A: Correspondence, Ephemera and Legal Documents, 1907-2004
Subseries 1: Julia Ruuttila's Correspondence
Subseries 2: Correspondence and Papers of Family Members
Subseries 3: Ephemera and Legal Papers
Subseries 4: Sandy Polishuk's Correspondence
Series B: Activism and Organizations, circa 1920-1988
Series C: Manuscripts, circa 1935-1991
Series D: Published Materials and Writings by Others, 1925-1990
Subseries 1: Published Materials
Subseries 2: Writings by Others
Series E: Research for Biography of Louise Bryant, 1878-1987
Subseries 1: Virginia Gardner
Subseries 2: Julia Ruuttila
Subseries 3: California and Nevada Research
Series F: Julia Ruuttila's FBI File, 1941-1993
The collection is open to the public.
Julia Ruuttila made several donations of papers to the Oregon Historical Society between 1970 and 1990. Sandy Polishuk donated papers she had collected from or copied from Ruuttila and her family, along with oral history audio tapes and FBI files that she used in writing Julia's biography. Arthur Spencer, a former librarian at the Oregon Historical Society, added correspondence that he had conducted with Ruuttila in the course of her research for journalism and book projects.
Gift of Julia Ruuttila, 1970-1990 (Accession nos.11735, 11755, 11785, 18187, 18677, and 20152). Gift of Sandy Polishuk (Accession no. 25451).
Photographic materials were separated into the Julia Ruuttila Photographs Collection (Organized Lot 700). Ruuttila's material on the Free Ray Becker Committee was separated into Mss2003. A large group of oral histories conducted by Sandy Polishuk with Julia Ruuttila, her friends, co-workers, and family members were transferred to the Oral History Collection (interviews with Ruuttila, SR11030.1-25; interviews with others, SR11031-11060; ILWU convention, SR11061; farewell luncheon, SR11062). Transcripts prepared by Polishuk are available. Some books that accompanied the collection were transferred to the Research Library Book Collection and are cataloged individually.
Gardner, Virginia. Friend and Lover: The Life of Louise Bryant. New York: Horizon Press, 1982.
Polishuk, Sandy. Sticking to the Union: An Oral History of the Life and Times of Julia Ruuttila. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2003.
The collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings:
Bertram, Maurice.; Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Bryant, Louise, 1885-1936; Gardner, Virginia.; Goodman, Irvin, 1897-1958; James, Cheryl D.; McDonald, Michael Jack.; Murnane, Francis J., 1914-1968; Polishuk, Sandy, 1940-; Ramp, Floyd Cleveland, 1882-1984; Ruuttila, Julia, 1907-1991; Ruuttila, Oscar.
Industrial Workers of the World.; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union.; International Woodworkers of America.; Oregon. State Public Welfare Commission.; Oregon State Employees Association.; United States. Congress. House. Un-American Activities Committee.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.
Civil rights--Oregon.; Labor movment--Oregon--History--20th century.; Labor unions--Northwest, Pacific--History--20th century.; Labor unions and communism--United States.; Peace movements--United States.; Women in politics--Northwest, Pacific.; Women journalists--Northwest, Pacific.; Women labor leaders--Northwest, Pacific.; Women labor union members--Oregon.; Women radicals--Oregon.; Women social reformers--Oregon.
Oregon; Portland; Women; Civil Activism; Civil Procedures and Court; Labor History; Labor Unions
Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Manuscripts.; Novels.; Poetry.; Speeches.
- Correspondence, Ephemera, and Legal Documents, 1907-2004; 1940-1988; Series A
  Selected correspondence between Julia Ruuttila and union associates, publishers and editors, friends, and relatives. The series includes Sandy Polishuk's correspondence with Julia and others in the course of writing Ruuttila's biography, Sticking to the Union. Also included in the series is a small quantity of ephemera and legal papers. The correspondents lists include only those who are fully identified; those identified only by first name are not listed. The series is organized into the following sub-series: 1) Julia Ruuttila's Correspondence, 2) Correspondence and Papers of Family Members, 3) Ephemera and Legal Papers, and 4) Sandy Polishuk's Correspondence.
  - Julia Ruuttila's Correspondence, 1927-1988; Sub-series 1
    - Outgoing Correspondence, 1946-1970 (Box-folder 1/1)
      Correspondents include: Allan Fletcher (Federated Press), Bishop A. Raymond Grant (Methodist Church, Portland, Oregon), Rev. Orval M. Whitman (Methodist Church, Astoria, Oregon), Ruova Anna Nevalainen (Helsinki, Finland), Charles Humboldt (Mainstream), William O. Walker and Carol Williams Walker (North Bend, Oregon), Morgan Coe (The Daily Astorian), James Aronson (National Guardian), Richard C. Berner (University of Washington Library), Ronald Roley (International Woodworkers of America, Portland, Oregon), Ed Mapes and R.J. Keenan (Columbia River District Council, IlWU, Portland, Oregon), Robert E. Burke (Pacific Northwest Quarterly), and Otto Hartwig.
    - Outgoing Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 1/2)
      Includes an autobiographical memo, dated April 6, 1978, addressed to "Danny," who requested a resumé to accompany a grant application to the National Endowment for the Humanities, possibly to support lectures by Julia.
      Correspondents include: Matt Cullen, Nancy Clay, Arthur Spencer (Oregon Historical Society Research Library), Earl B. Kirkland (Union Labor Retirement Association, Portland, Oregon), and President [Jimmy Carter?] re. nerve gas stored at the Umatilla Army Depot, Hermiston, Oregon.
    - Outgoing Correspondence, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 1/3)
      Includes correspondence seeking assistance for Julia's former granddaughter-in-law, Ruth Ruuttila, who had been seriously injured in a car accident.
      Correspondents include: Jerry Baum, International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (Portland, Oregon), John McClellan, Jr., and editor of the Oregonian.
    - Outgoing correspondence--to Valerie Taylor [and Norma Wyatt], 1961-1967 (Box-folder 1/4)
      Valerie Taylor was president of the Federated Auxiliaries of the ILWU for many years, Norma Wyatt was secretary, and Julia Ruuttila was in charge of publicity. Letters, which are photocopies obtained by Sandy Polishuk, also include Julia's news releases.
    - Incoming Correspondence, 1927-1958 (Box-folder 1/5)
      A 1927 letter from William Dietrich (Communist Party, Denver, Colorado), includes information on Julia's early union organizing among coal miners. A 1940 letter from Francis Murnane, president, announced her honorary life membership in the Plywood and Veneer Workers Union Local No. 9-102, Portland, Oregon.
      Other correspondents: Mary Heaton Vorse (Provincetown, Massachusetts), W.J. Baker (Plywood, Veneer and Box-Shook Council, International Woodworkers of America, Olympia, Washington), Ora Goodman, Miriam Kelkin, Irvin Goodman (Portland attorney), William Chester (International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, San Francisco, California), William Price (New York City), Al Richmond (publisher, People's World), Ben Anderson (Portland attorney), and Anne Braden (Southern Conference Educational Fund, Louisville, Kentucky).
    - Incoming Correspondence, 1962-1970 (Box-folder 1/6)
      Included are many letters and cards of condolence, from people representing all aspects of her life, on the unexpected death of Julia's husband, Oscar Ruuttila, in December 1962.
      Other correspondents include: Milton Meltzer (editor, Pediatric Herald), Morgan Coe (publisher, The Daily Astorian), James Aronson (editor, National Guardian), Richard C. Berner (University of Washington Library), Jean Van Erman (Seattle, Washington), Oona MacIver (The Dispatcher), Harold Symmonds (Astoria, Oregon), Robert E. Burke (Pacific Northwest Quarterly), Albert F. Gunns (University of Washington), Francis J. Murnane, Leo Coe, Millard McClung (Oregon Historical Society Library), and Lloyd Anderson (Portland city commissioner).
    - Incoming Correspondence, 1971-1987 (Box-folder 1/7)
      Includes circular letter in support of Julia Ruuttila and other Vietnam War protestors who had refused to pay their telephone tax that had been levied specifically to support the war. Also includes a get well card from Harry Bridges of the ILWU, with handwritten personal message.
      Other correspondents include: Millard McClung (Oregon Historical Society Library), Carl Haessler (Detroit, Michigan), Kenneth Porter (Eugene, Oregon), Tom Copeland (St. Paul, Minnesota), Valerie Seyffert (of Alcoholics Anonymous to The Dispatcher, praising article by Julia Ruuttila), C.H. Blyth (of International Transport Workers' Federation to Harry Bridges of the Longshoremen's Union praising article by Julia on plight of the crew of the ship, Elgreca), Juanita Scanlon (Salem, Oregon), Pedro Felipe Ramirez (Valparaiso, Chile--Spanish with English translation), Gloria T. Collantes (Manila, Philippines), Vernice Berg (Astoria, Oregon), Charles L. Geiger (Association of Western Pulp and Paper Workers, Oregon City Local 68), Harry Bridges, Lisa Uhlman ("Town Hall" KATU television program), Walter Sakai (of Portland Chapter Japanese American Citizens League to Curtis McClain, ILWU, San Francisco, copy to Julia Ruuttila), Thomas Vaughn (Oregon Historical Society), and James W. Overgaard (Union Labor Retirement Association).
    - Incoming correspondence re. stories and letters submitted to pulp magazines, 1957-1962 (Box-folder 1/8)
      McFadden Publications, including True Story and Cash Box, for which Julia Ruuttila's submissions won contests: "My Husband was Impotent", 1958; "Important Only to God," 1959; and "I Married an Old Country Finn," 1960.
      True Confessions.
  - Correspondence and Papers of Family Members, 1938-1963; Sub-series 2
    - Maurice Bertram (Julia's husband), 1938 (Box-folder 1/9)
      Includes note from Lumber and Sawmill Workers Union Local 3, Portland, Oregon, summoning him to meet with National Labor Relations Board, and a State Relief Committee of Oregon commodity distribution card.
    - Michael McDonald (Julia's son)
      - Photocopies of letters to his mother obtained by Sandy Polishuk, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Letters and telegrams to and from Julia about her son, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Doreen McDonald Martinez (Julia Ruuttila's daughter-in-law and mother of Shane McDonald Ruuttila), circa 1950-1963 (Box-folder 1/12)
        Photocopies of letters to Julia and Shane obtained by Sandy Polishuk.
      - Shane McDonald Ruuttila--correspondence re. adoption by Julia Ruuttila, 1963 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Oscar Ruuttila, 1950-1962
      - Correspondence, ephemera, greeting cards, and newspaper clippings of Oscar's letters to the editor. (Box-folder 1/14)
        Ephemera includes a hand annotated brochure, "The Exile of Hamish MacKay and William Mackie." Also included are personal letters and a magazine profile of Oscar with photo, all in Finnish (no translations).
      - Correspondence re. Coast Guard denial of Port Security card, 1951-1954 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Ephemera and Legal Documents, 1907-1973; Sub-series 3
    - Ephemera, 1946-1948; 1973
      - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees, Oregon State Employees Association, Portland Local No. 191--membership book, Julia Ruuttila, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 1/16)
      - CIO Convention, Portland, Oregon--press card, Kathleen Cronin of Federated Press, 1948 November 22-26 (Box-folder 1/16)
      - Bloody July Fifth parade and memorial service--sticker, 1973 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Legal documents, 1907-1972
      - Birth certificate (photocopy), Julia Evelyn Godman, 1907 April 26 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Marriage certificate (photocopy), William Clayton Bowen and Julia E. Godman, 1924 March 13 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Divorce decree (photocopy), Juulia Bowen from William Bowen, 1925 January 30 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Marriage certificate (certified copy), Maurice A. Bertram and Julia Godman, 1926 July 6 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Affidavit re. 1937 International Woodworkers of America strike, 1947 February 28 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Court summons to appear re. Shane Ruuttila's arrest in a protest at the Sheraton Motor Hotel, Portland, Oregon, 1966 December 21 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Papers re. Internal Revenue Service collection of federal telephone tax that Julia Ruuttila had refused to pay on principal, 1972 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Sandy Polishuk Correspondence, 1988-2004; Sub-series 4
    - Incoming correspondence from Julia Ruuttila, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 1/18-20)
    - Other correspondence--letters, emails, and notes, 1992-2004 (Box-folder 1/21)
      Correspondents include: John R. Godman (Huntsville, Alabama, Julia's brother), Valerie Taylor, Rickie Sollinger (Boulder, Colorado), Virginia Warner Brodine (to Richard Meigs, copy in Sandy Polishuk's files), Cindy Shadd (Clatsop County Circuit Court), Linda Showalter, and (Marietta College Library).
- Activism and Organizations, circa 1920-1988; Series B
  The largest part of this series represents Julia Ruuttila's activities with the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union and Federated Auxiliaries. The series is arranged alphabetically by names of activities and organizations.
  - Anti Tax Shifting League--flier, 1936 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Cheryl James Committee--leaflet and circular letter, 1972 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Columbia River Fishermen's Protective Union--flier, 1952 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Committee Against Higher Utility Rates--fliers, news clippings, press releases, 1975 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Council of Women of Organized Labor--convention program, Seattle, Washington, 1937 November 6-7 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Emergency Peace Mobilization, Chicago--program, 1935 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Free Ray Becker Committee--circular letter and letterhead (blank), 1936 (Box-folder 2/7)
    The Free Ray Becker Committee Records are collection number, Mss 2003, at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
  - House Un-American Activities Committee, 1956 November-December (Box-folder 2/8)
    Includes subpoena and letter requiring Julia Ruuttila to testify at hearings in Seattle, Washington, conducted by Representative Francis E. Walters of Pennsylvania. Also newspaper clippings reporting Julia's testimony and including a photograph of her.
  - Industrial unions organizing conference, Portland, Oregon--minutes, 1938 December 7 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Industrial Workers of the World (IWW or Wobblies), circa 1920; 1922; 1979
    - Membership book, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - "Preamble and Constitution", 1922 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Report by Mary Catherine Lamb of Centralia Massacre 60th anniversary commemoration, Montesano and Chehalis, Washington--from unidentified publication, 1979 November (Box-folder 2/10)
    - International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU) (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Convention reports, Vancouver, British Columbia, 1965 April 5 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Correspondence and testimony, 1966; circa 1970
    - Letter from Howard Bodine to Matt Meehan recalling struggle for health and welfare benefits, 1966 March 31 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Testimony by John J. Fougerouse, representing ILWU pensioners, to Portland City Council in favor of peace resolution, circa 1970 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Civil lawsuit against ILWU Local No. 8, Portland, Oregon, re. race discrimination, 1968-1969; 1993 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Fougerouse Defense Committee--pamphlet and letterhead (blank), 1951 (Box-folder 2/14)
    The committee was formed in response to an Immigration Service arrest and attempted deportation of John J. Fougerouse, Portland longshoreman.
  - Mechanization and Modernization Agreement--photo book, Men and Machines: A Story about Longshoring on the West Coast Waterfront, 1963 (Box-folder 2/15)
    Photographs by Otto Hagel, text by Louis Goldblatt. Published by the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union and the Pacific Maritime Association.
  - Federated Auxiliaries
    - Records and newspaper clippings, 1937; 1957-1969
      - Minutes of First City Wide Conference of Union Auxiliaries, Portland, Oregon, 1937 September 29 (Box-folder 2/16)
      - Constitution, 1957 April, and revision, 1965 (Box-folder 2/16)
      - "Never Underestimate the ILWU Women," The Dispatcher, 1959 March 13 (Box-folder 2/16)
      - Convention, San Francisco, California--letters and press releases, 1967 June (Box-folder 2/16)
      - "Longshore Auxiliary Lends Helping Hand" re. Portland housewives' meat boycott protesting high prices, People's World, 1969 August 1 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Handbook, 1965 (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Regional conference, Portland, Oregon--executive board meeting minutes and newspaper clippings, 1964 September 18-19 (Box-folder 2/18)
    - International Women's Day, Portland State University--program, 1973 March 7-8 (Box-folder 2/19)
      Lists Julia Ruuttila and Artha Adair speaking on "Working Women and History of International Women's Day."
    - International Woodworkers of America (IWA), 1937-1940
      - Manual, 1937 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - Resolution re. West Oregon Mill strike, 1937 March (Box-folder 2/20)
      - News bulletin re. AFL and CIO dispute at Plylock Plant, Portland, Oregon, 1937 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - President's Address by Harold J. Pritchett, second constitutional convention, Seattle, Washington, 1938 September 12-17 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - Newsletter, The Saw, re. West-Oregon Mill strike, 1938 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - Newspaper clippings re. West-Oregon Mill strike and other IWA issues and activities, including some about Julia Bertram, 1938; 1940 (Box-folder 2/20)
    - Labor for Jobs and Peace--organizational meeting minutes, 1971 March 11 (Box-folder 2/21)
    - Multnomah County Citizen Involvement Committee--newspaper, Conduit, 1988 (Box-folder 2/22)
    - National Lawyer's Guild--excerpt from Bulletin re. Harry Bridges trial (photocopy), 1938 (Box-folder 2/23)
    - Oregon Labor Press, 1941; undated (Box-folder 2/24)
      - Clipping (photocopy), "Free Speech and the Courts" by C.E.S. Wood, excerpt from brief in the case of Dr. Marie Equi, 1918 (Box-folder 2/24)
      - Pamphlet (photocopy)--The Enemy Within: Dealing with the Enemy within the gates--The Trojan Horses of the Democracies--the Communists, 1941 An original is located in Mss 1505; Labor Collection (Box-folder 2/24)
    - Oregon state, circa 1920; 1929
      - Industrial Accident Commission--pamphlet, Work-Accidents in Oregon, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2/25)